Okay. So now, let's discuss
the SSM Session Manager feature of Systems Manager.
So this allows you to start a secure shell
on your EC2 instances and on-premises servers
without having SSH access or the need for bastion host
or any SSH keys.
That means that the port 22 on your EC2 instances
is going to be closed because there is going to be
no need to do SSH to establish a secure shell
onto your EC2 instance.
That means better security.
So how does that work?
Well, the EC2 instance that we're going to show you
in a second has an SSM Agent
and that agent is connected to the Session Manager service.
So that means that our users can access
through the Session Manager service
these two instance and execute some commands on it.
This has support for Linux, macOS and Windows
and we can send log data to Amazon S3 or CloudWatch Logs
to make it super secure.
I think it'll make a lot more sense
when we do the hands-on so let's do it.
So let's have a look at the SSM Session Manager service,
but first, we need to launch an EC2 instance.
So let's launch an instance right now
and I will scroll down.
We will choose Amazon Linux 2 AMI, t2.micro.
We will not use any key pair.
And then I will disable SSH traffic.
So as you can see, my EC2 instance will have
a security group that allows nothing.
No HTTP, no HTTPS, no SSH.
Yet, we will be able to use an SSM Session Manager shell.
So what I need to do actually is
to attach an IAM instance profile to my instance
to allow it to talk to the SSM service.
So I have a few right here,
but I'm going to create a new one just to show the process.
So click on create a new IAM role profile.
Then let's create a role.
For a service on AWS, it will be Amazon EC2.
Click on next. Then, for permissions,
we're going to filter for SSM
and we will choose the Amazon SSM managed instance core.
So let's select this and click on next.
And then I will call it demo EC2 role for SSM,
which allows the EC2 instance to use this policy
to talk to the SSM service.
So this is necessary for my instance
to be managed by the SSM service
and so we can use the SSM Session Manager feature.
So now that this role is created,
we're going to refresh here and we're going to look
for this demo EC2 role for SSM.
Perfect. So let's go ahead
and now, create and launch our instance,
which is now launched
and it's going to boot.
And so the thing I have to check now is the SSM service.
So let's go into Systems Manager.
And on the left hand side,
you're going to look for Fleet Manager
and Fleet Manager is a service where all the EC2 instances
that are registered with SSM will appear here.
So they're called managed nodes.
And as you can see right now,
we don't have any managed nodes,
but we need to wait for the EC2 instance to boot up
and then it will appear right here.
Okay. So I just refreshed and as you can see,
there's one instance. It's running.
We can see the SSM Agent is online.
We can see the platform, the operating system,
Amazon Linux 2, the SSM Agent version
and then links to the EC2 instance if we wanted to.
Okay. So as soon as our instance is under Fleet Manager,
that means that we're ready
to run a secure shell against it.
So to do so, I will scroll down
and I will look for Session Manager.
Now, Session Manager is a way for us
to access our Linux instances and Windows instances.
So let's start a session.
And as you can see here, okay,
my EC2 instance under the security group
does not have any inbound rule.
Okay. So zero inbound rules in here.
So let's start a session on this EC2 instance and start it.
And the idea is that we're going to get a secure shell,
as you'll see in a second.
Here we go, we have a secure shell
and I didn't need to have SSH access
so I can do ping google.com
and this command is going to work, obviously.
And if I do host to get the host name, so host name,
we can see that this is IP 172-31-1-148,
which is exactly corresponding to,
and if you go into networking,
the private IP address of my instance.
So that means that using the SSM secure shell,
we're able to have indeed a secure shell directly
from AWS without having SSH security keys and SSH access.
So to summarize, we have three ways
of accessing our EC2 instance.
Number one is to open the port 22 and then use SSH keys
and with a terminal to do the SSH command.
Number two is to use EC2 Instance Connect
and that didn't require to get SSH keys
because they will be temporarily uploaded
onto the Amazon EC2 instance if we need to.
So that was number two, but this required still
the port 22 to be opened on our EC2 instance
to have access with using EC2 Instance Connect.
And then we've explored the third option
which is Session Manager.
So we need to make sure that we had an EC2 instance
with Amazon Linux 2 and make sure
that this EC2 instance had an IAM role
and this IAM role, okay, as you can see under security,
had an IAM role and this IAM role allowed access
from the EC2 instance to Systems Manager
and this is what allowed us to get the secure shell running.
So that's it for this lecture.
We can terminate this session and the cool thing is
that the session history will be saved in terms of logs.
So we can see the session history right here.
So this is awesome.
And to finish, just take your instance and terminate it.
That's it.
I hope you like this lecture
and I will see you in the next lecture.